Guide to the Askanase family papers, 1948-2013 MS 776
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Askanase Family papers
1948-2013
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Askanase family
MS 776
.50 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection includes one box of personal correspondence, certificates, newspaper and newsletter clippings, photographs, memorabilia, and a scrapbook that document the activities of Reuben Askanase, Hilda Graham Askanase, David Askanase, and Susan Askanase between 1948 and 2013.
Biographical / Historical
Reuben W. Askanase was born October 21, 1908, in Fargo, North Dakota to immigrant parents. Early in life he assisted his mother with the family's chuck wagon -- following migrant workers, cooking and serving them meals on their jobs or boarding many in their home. Following graduation from North Dakota Agricultural College, Askanase moved to Brooklyn and took a position as an office boy at Abraham & Strauss department store, where he met his future wife, Hilda Graham. Over the following years he worked his way up to vice president of the company.
Hilda Graham Askanase was born October 12, 1906, in Old Town, Maine. She received her Bachelor of Science degree from the University of Maine with a major in French and was a member of the honorary societies Phi Beta Kappa and Phi Kappa Phi. As mentioned, Graham met Reuben Askanase while at Abraham & Strauss, and the two married in 1931, in Akron, Ohio. They remained in Ohio for several years – having two children there, Phyllis and David. Hilda and Ruben moved back to New York briefly before making their final move to Houston in 1945.
After arriving in Houston, Reuben began working with the Columbia Dry Goods store and invested in the purchase of the manufacturer of Evenflow baby bottles. He and his partners built the company into Dunhill International, which owned Spaulding sporting goods, along with other properties. He was active in the Houston Council on Human Relations, the Houston Symphony, and the Alley Theatre. He also served as president of the Houston Sports Association and the Jewish Community Center, chairman of the United Jewish Campaign, trustee of the Rothko Chapel and North Dakota State University (formerly NDAC), and a board member of Allied Mercantile Bank and Benjamin Franklin Savings Association. Reuben received the Max H. Nathan Award for community service from the American Jewish Committee in 1964.
The two were known for their philanthropy, both in the Jewish community and throughout Houston. They helped raise funds for Citizens for Good Schools and the Houston Area Women's Center, among others. Reuben and Hilda were members of Congregation Beth Israel.
Reuben Askanase died January 3, 1991, and Hilda on Aug. 4, 2013, in Houston and are interred at the Beth Israel Cemetery. Their son, David James Askanase, was born June 28, 1936 in Akron, Ohio. He graduated from University of Pennsylvania in 1958 and Harvard Law School in 1962. He married Susan Ellen Silverman in Ohio in 1963. David was a practicing attorney in Houston for many years before retiring.
Scope and Contents
One box of personal correspondence, certificates, newspaper and newsletter clippings, photographs, memorabilia, and a scrapbook document the activities of four members of the Askanase family from 1948 to 2013. Of particular interest is personal correspondence from George Bush and Lloyd Bentsen, a scrapbook belonging to Reuben Askanase that includes newspaper clippings and photographs recording his community involvement in the Houston area, and a panoramic photo of the 1954 San Jacinto High School graduating class.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Susan and David Askanase, July 2, 2018.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in five series as follows:
Series I: Reuben Askanase; Series II: Hilda Askanase; Series III: David Askanase; Series IV: Susan Askanase; Series V: Addendum
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
photographs; personal correspondence; certificates; programs (documents); clippings (information artifacts); memorabilia; scrapbooks
Places
North Dakota State University
Subjects (Persons)
Askanase, Hilda (Graham); Askanase, Reuben; Bush, George
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Beth Israel (Houston, Tex.); Houston Astros
- Series I: Reuben Askanase, 1950-1991
  - Certificate from Guardians of Israel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Handwritten note from Congressman George Bush, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Houston Astros program, "Askanase Named Chariman of the Board", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Howard Binford's Guide", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lyndon Baines Johnson Inaugural Prayer from Hyman Judah Schactel, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph - David H. White JCC Award, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photo Album - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Resolution of High Esteem and Gratitude from Beth Israel (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook (photographs included), 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Hilda Askanase, 1948-1950
  - Certificates to Mrs. Reuben Askanase, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photograph taken in the lobby of the Rice Hotel with M.J. Dittmar (calf scramble winner), 1948-02-08 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series III: David Askanase, 1948-1974
  - Certificate from United Jewish Appeal, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Confirmation materials (group photograph included), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence regarding "Susholtz Young Leadership Award", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters (3) from Congressman George Bush, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter clippings (Beth Israel Board of Directors and Saturday School), 1948; 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1954-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs - Federation of Young Professionals, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sigma Alpha Rho photo, dinner at the Shamrock Hotel, c. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Panoramic Photograph - 1954 graduating class of San Jacinto High School (Map-drawer 189)
- Series IV: Susan Askanase, n.d.
  - Jewish Herald Voice press card, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series V: Addendum, 1987-2013
  - Correspondence from President George H.W. Bush and Senator Lloyd Bentsen, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The original letters have been removed and placed in the control folder.
  - Photocopied of news clippings, 1987-2013 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "The Center News" newsletter, 1990-05-07 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photographs (2) taken at JCC Max Nathan award event with Reuben Askanase, recipient, 1990-05-17 (Box 1, Folder 24)